<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">38767534</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1998-3689</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>72</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Indian journal of ophthalmology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Indian J Ophthalmol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Guidelines for setting up low-vision and rehabilitation services in India.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1580</StartPage><EndPage>1585</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1580-1585</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/IJO.IJO_2712_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Low vision and blindness are increasing public health issues impacting individuals' quality of life. During clinical low-vision services, vision rehabilitation is crucial for enhancing daily living skills and improving life quality. Low-vision and rehabilitation (LVR) services encompass comprehensive measures that aid visually disabled individuals in restoring function, autonomy, and social participation. Such holistic management requires a multidisciplinary approach, facilitating adaptation to environmental and sociocultural changes. However, the lack of awareness about the principles and practices of LVR services poses a major hindrance to setting up such a special clinic in the eye hospital. This article is about a consensus statement on the guidelines for establishing LVR services focusing on basic requirements, especially in low-resource countries. The present recommendation to set up an LVR clinic was made after group discussions and debates among various experts and stakeholders during the National Workshop on Strengthening Low-Vision and Rehabilitation Services organized at Dr. Rajendra Prasad Centre for Ophthalmic Sciences, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi. The event was participated by many ophthalmologists and optometrists coming from across the country. The recommendations required at the tertiary level are outlined under the four headings: Human resources and training: two ophthalmologists, that is, a low vision specialist or a well-experienced in low vision and one who has received one-week orientation and training, one optometrist, one rehabilitation supervisor, and two rehabilitation assistants; Assessment equipment: basic screening and diagnostic; Assistive devices for low vision, including, digital and non-digital; Assistive devices for rehabilitation, and methods for records maintenance. The institution may not follow strictly the present guidelines but will provide an idea on LVR services initiation.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2024 Copyright: &#xa9; 2024 Indian Journal of Ophthalmology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Senjam</LastName><ForeName>Suraj Singh</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dr. Rajendra Prasad Centre for Ophthalmic Sciences, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tandon</LastName><ForeName>Radhika</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vashist</LastName><ForeName>Praveen</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mounica</LastName><ForeName>B</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gupta</LastName><ForeName>Vivek</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aggarwal</LastName><ForeName>Sneha</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016446">Consensus Development Conference</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Indian J Ophthalmol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0405376</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0301-4738</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001766" MajorTopicYN="N">Blindness</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000534" MajorTopicYN="N">rehabilitation</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007194" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">India</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009885" MajorTopicYN="N">Ophthalmology</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000592" MajorTopicYN="N">standards</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017410" MajorTopicYN="N">Practice Guidelines as Topic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011788" MajorTopicYN="N">Quality of Life</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015354" MajorTopicYN="Y">Vision, Low</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000534" MajorTopicYN="N">rehabilitation</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38767534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/IJO.IJO_2712_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">02223307-202472110-00009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>The Gazette of India Extraordinary Part-II-section 3-Sub-section ii, January 5, 2018. REGD.N.L33004/99. Available from: https://www.swavlambancard.gov.in/public/files/ProceduresGuidelines.pdf . [Last accessed on 2023 Oct 18].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourne RRA, Flaxman SR, Braithwaite T, Cicinelli MV, Das A, Jonas JB, et al. Vision Loss Expert Group. Magnitude, temporal trends, and projections of the global prevalence of blindness and distance and near vision impairment: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Glob Health 2017;5:e888&#x2013;97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourne R, Steinmetz JD, Flaxman S, Briant PS, Taylor HR, Resnikof S, et al. Trends in prevalence of blindness and distance and near vision impairment over 30 years: An analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study. Lancet Global Health 2021;9:e130&#x2013;43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehrlich JR, Agarwal A, Young C, Lee J, Bloom DE. The prevalence of vision impairment and blindness among older adults in India: Findings from the Longitudinal Ageing Study in India. Nat Aging 2022;2:1000&#x2013;7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vashist P, Senjam SS, Gupta V, Gupta N, Shamanna BR, Wadhwani M, et al. Blindness and visual impairment and their causes in India: Results of a nationally representative survey. PLoS One 2022;17:e0271736.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krahn GL. WHO World Report on Disability: A review. Disabil Health J 2011;4:141&#x2013;2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan T, Friedman DS, Bradley C, Massof R. Estimates of incidence and prevalence of visual impairment, low vision, and blindness in the United States. JAMA Ophthalmol 2018;136:12&#x2013;9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manna S, Grover S, Senjam SS, Vashist P. An overview on paediatric low vision and rehabilitation. Delhi J Ophthalmol 2022;32:72&#x2013;81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Binns AM, Bunce C, Dickinson C, Harper R, Tudor-Edwards R, Woodhouse M, et al. How effective is low vision service provision? A systematic review. Survey Ophthalmol 2012;57:34&#x2013;65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stelmack JA, Tang XC, Reda DJ, Moran DA, Rinne S, Mancil RM, et al. The Veterans Affairs Low Vision Intervention Trial (LOVIT): Design and methodology. Clin Trials 2007;4:650&#x2013;60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senjam SS, Foster A, Bascaran C, Vashist P. Awareness, utilization and barriers in accessing assistive technology among young patients attending a low vision rehabilitation clinic of a tertiary eye care centre in Delhi. Indian J Ophthalmol 2019;67:1548&#x2013;54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiang PP, Marella M, Ormsby G, Keeffe J. Critical issues in implementing low vision care in the Asia-Pacific region. Indian J Ophthalmol 2012;60:456&#x2013;9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Court H, Ryan B, Bunce C, Margrain TH. How effective is the new community-based Welsh low vision service? Br J Ophthalmol 2011;95:178&#x2013;84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson ML, Virgili G, Shepherd JD, Di Nome MA, Fletcher DC, Kaleem MA, et al. American Academy of Ophthalmology Preferred Practice Pattern Vision Rehabilitation Committee. Vision Rehabilitation Preferred Practice Pattern. Ophthalmology 2023;130:P271&#x2013;P335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leat S. 2020 CAO clinical practice guideline: Optometric low vision rehabilitation full guidelines. Canadian J Optometry 2020;82:19&#x2013;62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinds A, Sinclair A, Park J, Suttie A, Paterson H, Macdonald M. Impact of an interdisciplinary low vision service on the quality of life of low vision patients. Br J Ophthalmol 2003;87:1391&#x2013;6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudduck G, Corcoran H, Davies K. Developing an integrated paediatric low vision service. Ophthalmic Physiol Opt 2004;24:323&#x2013;6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal R, Tripathi A. Current modalities for low vision rehabilitation. Cureus 2021;13:e16561.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gimigliano F, Negrini S. The World Health Organization &#x201c;Rehabilitation 2030: A call for action&#x201d;. Eur J Phys Rehabil Med 2017;53:155&#x2013;68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senjam SS, Foster A, Bascaran C. Assistive technology for visual impairment and trainers at schools for the blind in Delhi. Assist Technol 2022;34:418&#x2013;22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pollard TL, Simpson JA, Lamoureux EL, Keeffe JE. Barriers to accessing low vision services. Ophthalmic Physiol Opt 2003;23:321&#x2013;7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O&#x2019;Connor PM, Lamoureux EL, Keeffe JE. Predicting the need for low vision rehabilitation services. Br J Ophthalmol 2008;92:252&#x2013;5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott IU, Smiddy WE, Schiffman J, Feuer WJ, Pappas CJ. Quality of life of low-vision patients and the impact of low-vision services. Am J Ophthalmol 1999;128:54&#x2013;62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fontenot JL, Bona MD, Kaleem MA, McLaughlin WM Jr, Morse AR, Schwartz TL, et al. American Academy of Ophthalmology Preferred Practice Pattern Vision Rehabilitation Committee. Vision rehabilitation preferred practice pattern&#xae;. Ophthalmology 2018;125:P228&#x2013;78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senjam SS, Manna S. National Workshop on Strengthening Low Vision and Rehabilitation Services, Technical Report 2019. doi: 10.13140/RG.2.2.35419.54564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senjam SS, Vashist P, Gupta V. Workshop National Action Plan for Low Vision and Rehabilitation- Nurturing Leadership, Technical Report 2015. doi: 10.13140/RG.2.2.27257.03686.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiang PP, O&#x2019;Connor PM, Le Mesurier RT, Keeffe JE. A global survey of low vision service provision. Ophthalmic Epidemiol 2011;18:109&#x2013;21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senjam SS. Developing a disability inclusive model for low vision service. Indian J Ophthalmol 2021;69:417&#x2013;422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Nispen RM, Virgili G, Hoeben M, Langelaan M, Klevering J, Keunen JE, et al. Low vision rehabilitation for better quality of life in visually impaired adults. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2020;1:CD006543.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bentley SA, Jackson AJ, Johnston AW, Napper GA, Hodgson M, Soong GP, et al. Advancing low vision services: A plan for Australian optometry. Clin Exp Optom 2014;97:214&#x2013;20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan B, White S, Wild J, Court H, Margrain TH. The newly established primary care based Welsh Low Vision Service is effective and has improved access to low vision services in Wales. Ophthalmic Physiol Opt 2010;30:358&#x2013;64.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>